<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Israel Study Tour</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2010 04:16:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7</generator>
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">180112064</site>	<item>
		<title>Israel Trip</title>
		<link>./../2009/02/israel-trip/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../2009/02/israel-trip/index.html#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2009 01:18:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Itinerary]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://192.168.1.90/israel/?p=31</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Later this week I am going to Israel for the first time.&#0160; Now is an exciting time, to say the least:&#0160; the violence in Gaza, Israeli elections, the economic downturn.&#0160; What?&#0160; Am I nuts?&#0160;&#0160; What better time to go! It’s my first time and I am doing a lot: Private touring: (February 21-25) Jerusalem:&#0160; the [&#038;hellip]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Later this week I am going to Israel for the first time.&#0160; Now is an exciting time, to say the least:&#0160; the violence in Gaza, Israeli elections, the economic downturn.&#0160; What?&#0160; Am I nuts?&#0160;&#0160; What better time to go!</p>
<p>It’s my first time and I am doing a lot:</p>
<ul>
<li>Private touring: (February 21-25)
<ul>
<li>Jerusalem:&#0160; the birthplace of Western Religion(s) (3)
<li>Masada:&#0160; the last stance and suicide of Jewish defenders against Rome
<li>Qumran:&#0160; site of the Dead Sea Scrolls excavation
<li>the Galilee:&#0160; hills and forests
<li>Haifa, Ceasarea, and Akko (Accre):&#0160; in order, Jews and Israeli Arabs co-existing peacefully and the largest Baha’i temple; Roman ruins; the most Arab of Israeli cities </li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</ul>
<li>Jordan tour (February 26-28):&#0160;
<ul>
<li>Amman, ancient Philadelphia and the capital of Jordan
<li>Madaba (settled for 4500 years) and most important Christian center in Jordan
<li>Mt. Nebo, where Moses first saw the Promised Land
<li>Kerak, a crusader castle—thankfully the only one I’ll bother with
<li>Petra, ancient capital of the Nabateans carved out of rock in the 4th century BCE—and one of the filming locations for Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade </li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</li>
</ul>
<p><span id="more-31"></span></p>
<ul>
<li>Study Tour with the New Israel Fund (<a href="http://www.nif.org/" target="_blank">link</a>) in Jerusalem, Galilee, Tel Aviv, Negev, Ashdod (March 1-10) :
<ul>
<li>“Current Challenges Facing Israeli Society,” Professor Naomi Chazan, NIF president and former speaker of the Knesset
<li>“Safeguarding Democracy and Human Rights in Israel,” Association of Civil Rights in Israel
<li>Visit to Supreme Court of Israel (which recently blocked an attempt to prevent Arab parties from participating in elections to the Knesset)
<li>Meeting with members of the Knesset (Israel’s parliament) from different parties
<li>Tour of Jerusalem’s Nachlaot area (neighborhood built just outside the old Jewish quarter)
<li>One City for Two People:&#0160; tour of the heinous separation barrier built by Ariel Sharon and Ehud Olmert
<li>tour of Ofrah, one of the earliest Jewish settlements in the Occupied Territories of the West Bank, including a meeting with a defender of the settlements
<li>tour of Gedera, a Jewish Ethiopian community
<li>“Status of Women in Israel Today,” Anat Hoffman, Director of the Israel Religious Action Center of the Reform Movement
<li>tour of Moshav Kerem Maharal—a moshav is a cooperative agricultural community centered on families, often with private ownership of farm plots
<li>relax at a spa in the Galilee
<li>“Promoting Democracy Education”
<li>tour of Safed, early Jewish settlement, home of Kabbalah—Jewish mysticism, conquered by the crusaders and then the Mamluks.&#0160; It is now Israel’s art capital.
<li>visit Emek HaEleh Winery, with samples?
<li>“Religious Pluralism,” Professor Moshe Halbertal
<li>Shabbat service
<li>tour old city of Jerusalem
<li>“Outlook for Peace – a Palestinian’s Perspective,” Professor <strong>Sari Nusseibeh</strong> of Al Quds University and author of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Once-Upon-Country-Palestinian-Life/dp/0374299501" target="_blank">Once Upon a Country</a>, an absolutely fabulous book by a delightfully thoughtful man—this will be <em>the</em> highlight for me.
<li>“An Israeli Journalist’s Perspective on the Current Mood in Israel,” Isabel Kershner of the New York Times
<li>“Current Issues in Human Trafficking and Refugees,” Shevy Korzen of the Hotline for Migrant Workers
<li>“Community and Business Partnerships for Social Change,” Shula Keshet
<li>view Bauhaus architecture in Tel Aviv
<li>dinner with Israel government spokesperson, Miri Eisen
<li>“Addressing the Needs of the Negev in Be’er Sheva,” Yarona Ben Shalom
<li>“Economic Empowerment for Bedouin Women at Sidreh,” a Bedouin village in the Negev Desert in Israel’s south
<li>tour Ashdod, Israel’s primary port on the Mediterranean Sea
<li>tour Diaspora Museum – the “Diaspora” refers to the spreading out of a people from its ancestral home. For Jews, the original Diaspora was the flight to Babylon.
<li>tour Natan Guttman museum </li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Phew!&#0160; What a trip!&#0160; I’m not tired; I’m energized.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../2009/02/israel-trip/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">31</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Map of Israel</title>
		<link>./../2009/02/map-of-israel/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../2009/02/map-of-israel/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2009 01:19:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Maps]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://192.168.1.90/israel/?p=30</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here is a map to get you oriented.  I’ll look for some others that may highlight the regions and key locations better.  In fact, I’ll find one that I can put pushpins in for each place I’ve visited]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is a map to get you oriented.  I’ll look for some others that may highlight the regions and key locations better.  In fact, I’ll find one that I can put pushpins in for each place I’ve visited.</p>
<p><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/map-of-Israel.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-101" title="map of Israel" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/map-of-Israel.png" alt="" width="448" height="885" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../2009/02/map-of-israel/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">30</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reading List</title>
		<link>./../2009/02/reading-list/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../2009/02/reading-list/index.html#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2009 16:33:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://192.168.1.90/israel/?p=28</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Going on a trip like this, focused so much on political tension, requires deepening one’s understanding of the history of the region and the ideas and beliefs that provide context for the conflict.&#0160; I expanded my previous readings to include more consideration for Palestinian views. New for this trip: Once Upon a Country—A Palestinian Life, [&#038;hellip]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Going on a trip like this, focused so much on political tension, requires deepening one’s understanding of the history of the region and the ideas and beliefs that provide context for the conflict.&#0160; I expanded my previous readings to include more consideration for Palestinian views.</p>
<p>New for this trip:</p>
<p><em>Once Upon a Country—A Palestinian Life</em>, Sari Nusseibeh with Anthony David</p>
<p><em>Shared Histories—A Palestinian-Israeli Dialogue,</em> Paul Scham, Walid Salem, Benjamin Pogrund (eds.)</p>
<p><em>Sleeping on a Wire—Conversations with Palestinians in Israel,</em> afterword by David Grossman</p>
<p><em>The Accidental Empire—Israel and the Birth of the Settlements, 1967-1977</em>, Gershom Gorenberg</p>
<p><em>A Tale of Love and Darkness, </em>Amos Oz</p>
<p><em>Lords of the Land</em>, Zeital and Eldar</p>
<p><em>Dreams and Shadows,</em> Wright</p>
<p><em>The Missing Peace,</em> Dennis Ross</p>
<p></p>
<p>Other books I’ve previously read to understand the longer term view of the conflict include:</p>
<p><em>Righteous Victims</em>, Benny Morris.&#0160; Probably the best one volume history of Jewish settlement in Israel/Palestine and the long-term emergence of the conflict.&#0160;&#0160; His other books are very worthwhile, especially <em>1948</em></p>
<p><em>Scars of War, Wounds of Peace,</em> Shlomo Ben-Ami.&#0160; An insider’s history of Israeli politics of the peace process by Ehud Barak’s foreign minister during the Camp David talks sponsored by President Clinton.</p>
<p><em>Islam in the World</em>, Malise Ruthven.&#0160;&#0160; An excellent survey of what Muslims believe and the many interwoven threads of Islamic belief over the years.&#0160; Much better than, “the Quran says…”</p>
<p><em>A History of the Arab Peoples,</em> Albert Hourani</p>
<p><em>The Battle for God</em>, Karen Armstrong</p>
<p></p>
<p>And of course, the indispensable intellectual illumination to finding a way to resolve cultural conflict—the works of Isaiah Berlin, including:</p>
<p><em>Four Essays on Liberty</em></p>
<p><em>The Crooked Timber of Humanity: Chapters in the History of Ideas</em></p>
<p>All of Berlin’s books and essays are worthwhile and challenging.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../2009/02/reading-list/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">28</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Arrival</title>
		<link>./../2009/02/arrival/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../2009/02/arrival/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2009 12:06:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Chron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://192.168.1.90/israel/?p=27</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Well, I made it.  Flights on time, no problems.  Finished The Accidental Empire.  Got into Sleeping on a Wire.  Watched two free movies.  Maybe it wasn’t such a good idea to watch “Body of Lies” with Leo DiCaprio.  It’s about CIA collaboration with Jordanian secret service.  Hopefully, they won’t ask about my recent movie watching [&#038;hellip]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Well, I made it.  Flights on time, no problems.  Finished The Accidental Empire.  Got into Sleeping on a Wire.  Watched two free movies.  Maybe it wasn’t such a good idea to watch “Body of Lies” with Leo DiCaprio.  It’s about CIA collaboration with Jordanian secret service.  Hopefully, they won’t ask about my recent movie watching when I cross over into Jordan next week.</p>
<p>Miraculously, I got to the hotel driving through Jerusalem in pitch black and pouring down rain using only the Hertz map. Jerusalem is probably not an easy place to get around in broad daylight;  it’s interesting at night.  Went past lots of interesting looking theatres and museums;  maybe I’ll get to see some while I mtn. bike around Jerusalem with my guide—he made me bring my cleated shoes.</p>
<p><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/arrival.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-61" title="arrival" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/arrival-300x225.png" alt="" width="300" height="225" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/arrival-300x225.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/arrival.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>
<p><span id="more-27"></span></p>
<p>Had dinner at the hotel.  Old world meets Middle East:  hummous and other middle eastern choices or right from the shtetl: smoked white fish, gefilte fish, personal mini-challahs, tsimmes (finely chopped carrots with onions).  Topped off with a rather young and markedly tart Merlot from the Golan Heights—not quite ready to compete on the international market.</p>
<p><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/Dan-hotel.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-70" title="Dan hotel" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/Dan-hotel-225x300.png" alt="" width="225" height="300" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/Dan-hotel-225x300.png 225w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/Dan-hotel.png 360w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></a></p>
<p>Each room in the hotel has its very own individual mezuzah on the doorpost.  Yes, it’s a Jewish country.</p>
<p><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/mezuzah.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-105" title="mezuzah" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/mezuzah-225x300.png" alt="" width="225" height="300" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/mezuzah-225x300.png 225w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/mezuzah.png 360w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../2009/02/arrival/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">27</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Situation</title>
		<link>./../2009/02/the-situation/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../2009/02/the-situation/index.html#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2009 12:39:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Background]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://192.168.1.90/israel/?p=26</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How did the situation between Israel and Palestine begin?&#0160; Where is it now and why has it remained so hard to resolve? Skipping the ancient period through most of the Islamic and Turkish periods, European Jews began to settle in Palestine in the 1880s, driven by religious motivation, the oppression of Russian pogroms against Jews, [&#038;hellip]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>How did the situation between Israel and Palestine begin?&#0160; Where is it now and why has it remained so hard to resolve? </p>
<p>Skipping the ancient period through most of the Islamic and Turkish periods, European Jews began to settle in Palestine in the 1880s, driven by religious motivation, the oppression of Russian pogroms against Jews, and general hostility of European countries towards Jews.&#0160; But, it was just a trickle.&#0160; The first Jews generally settled in Jerusalem and bought land from Turkish landlords as Palestine was nominally under control of the Ottoman empire.&#0160; </p>
<p>In 1917, the Balfour Declaration committed England, very reluctantly and tentatively, to creating a Jewish homeland in Palestine&#8211;a nation for Jews with a Jewish identity,&quot;<em>His Majesty&#39;s government view with favour the establishment in Palestine of a national home for the Jewish people,</em>&quot; with the understanding that &quot;<em>nothing shall be done which may prejudice the civil and religious rights of existing non-Jewish communities in Palestine, or the rights and political status enjoyed by Jews in any other country.”</em>&#0160; At the end of World War I with the fall of the Ottoman Empire, France and England split up Turkey&#39;s former middle eastern territories in a secret treaty.&#0160; In 1921, England received control over present day Israel and Jordan, which it then called Trans-Jordan.&#0160; Jewish settlement increased, still by purchasing land from Turks or Arabs. </p>
<p>The problem of how Jews and Arabs and a few Christians would live in the land together existed from the very beginning and the earliest Jewish settlers were aware of it.&#0160; The same possible answers existed then as now, but a truly workable answer was always put off&#8211;then as now.&#0160; Jews and Arabs could live side by side in one state that recognized full rights for all.&#0160; Not clear was who would be in control of such a state:&#0160; Jews or Arabs?&#0160; The other alternative was to split the land into separate portions with each separately controlled by Arabs and Jews.&#0160; How to split the overall territory, how to determine who got what, and how the people left in the &quot;other&quot; territory would be protected were never figured out. </p>
</p>
<p><span id="more-26"></span></p>
<p>After World War II and the Holocaust, in which over five million Jews died, the urgency for finding a safe homeland for the remaining Jews of Europe increased.&#0160; Also, Arab states were influenced by Nazi propaganda so that Jews in Iraq, Iran, and Syria felt unsafe remaining there.&#0160; Jews already in Israel, with support from Jews in England, tried to bring more Jews from Europe to Palestine.&#0160; The British wanted to minimize conflicts between Jews and Arabs, so the British troops stationed in Palestine tried to prevent Jewish immigration.&#0160; Jews in England, Israel, and the United States worked in the United Nations to push for a partition of Trans-Jordan into a portion for Jews and a portion for Arabs.&#0160; </p>
<p>In 1947, the UN voted for the partition.&#0160; Both Arabs and Jews were concerned about what part of the land and how much land they would get.&#0160; Jerusalem and other parts of the West Bank of the Jordan River, including Bethlehem, Nazareth, and Hebron, were major concerns because all contain religious sites of profound importance in the history of Judaism, Christianity, and Islam.&#0160; Both Arabs and Jews began fighting each other and alternately fighting the British or seeking British assistance. The British knew a bloody conflict would ensue and wanted no part of it.&#0160; They were right.&#0160; Soon after Partition, violence on both sides escalated.&#0160; Arab forces invaded to attempt to take over the Jewish portion.&#0160; Jews used terror to expel Arabs from the Jewish portion.&#0160; The Jews had already organized the beginnings of a government and an army, while the Arabs still lived in family-based clans or villages.&#0160; The Jews fought back the Arabs and extended their territory beyond the UN partition lines&#8211;establishing what became known as the &quot;Green Line.&quot;&#0160; Most Arabs fled or were driven from the Jewish portion, which was established as the independent nation of Israel in 1948. </p>
<p>Three more wars were fought.&#0160; In 1956, Egypt, Syria, Jordan, and Iraq invaded Israel.&#0160; With support from England and France, Israel repelled the attacks and took over most of the Sinai Peninsula and the Suez Canal.&#0160; In the peace settlement, England, France, and the US sought to keep the Suez Canal open and asked Israel to give back the Sinai Peninsula in return for stationing UN peace-keepers near Suez and near the tip of Sinai to ensure that Egypt could not block Israeli shipping.&#0160; </p>
<p>In 1967, Egypt, Jordan, and Syria again invaded Israel.&#0160; In 6 days, Israel destroyed the entire Egyptian and Syrian air forces and destroyed nearly all of Egypt and Syria&#39;s tanks.&#0160; Israel won the Sinai Peninsula from Egypt, the West Bank from Jordan, and the Golan Heights from Syria.&#0160; Israel intended to hold these territories in order to achieve recognition of Israel&#39;s right to exist, lasting peace, and full diplomatic relations with the surrounding Arab countries.&#0160; But, the stunning victory lead some in Israel to believe that they could hold these territories forever&#8211;some believed this would ensure Israel&#39;s security and some believed that this would enable Israel to return to the Jewish lands described in the Old Testament.&#0160;&#0160; </p>
<p>In 1973, Egypt and Syria invaded Israel again in a surprise attack.&#0160; Israel was caught off guard and suffered defeats for 2 days.&#0160; By the third day, Israel regained the advantage and beat back the attacks—no territory changed hands or was returned.&#0160; But, Israel felt that it would always be vulnerable to attack, which became part of the Israeli ethos.</p>
<p>Of course, Arabs already lived in the occupied&#0160;territories and the Arab population is growing faster than the Jewish population, despite extensive immigration of Jews from the former Soviet Union during the 1980s and 1990s.&#0160; Once again the problem of who could live where and who would control territory was obvious but without a solution. In 1974, the PLO (Palestinian Liberation Organization) was recognized as the sole legitimate spokesman for the Arabs of Palestine.&#0160; At that time, the PLO&#39;s goal was to regain all of Palestine, reverse the UN partition, and eliminate Israel.&#0160; In 1979, Anwar Sadat, the leader of Egypt, offered full recognition and peace to Israel in return for Israel returning the Sinai Peninsula to Egypt.&#0160; Israel continued to hold the Gaza strip at the southwest end of Israel, the West Bank of the Jordan, Jerusalem, and the Golan Heights.&#0160; People in Israel, especially orthodox Jews, feared that they would be pressured to give up more territory.&#0160; So, they began to increase settlements in these territories for several reasons, real or pretended:&#0160; to help defend Israel against her Arab neighbors, to put Jews in the territories to weaken Palestinian control to increase the chances of holding the land forever, and to fulfill a distorted, false and essentially racist religious vision based on their interpretation of the Old Testament that God had promised all of the land of Canaan to the Jews. </p>
<p>The problem with the settlements was that most Jews didn&#39;t want to settle there and the settlements took land from Arabs and interfered with Arabs&#39; ability to get around and work.&#0160; Instead of providing more security, the settlements reduced security because the Jewish settlements were often deliberately placed in the middle of densely populated Arab areas and needed to be defended.&#0160; While right wing Israelis wanted to increase settlement and some Palestinians wanted to eliminate Israel, other Israelis and Palestinians believed they could find a way to create peace.&#0160; Just as in the beginning, there were only two potential solutions:&#0160; either one &quot;bi-national&quot; state with full rights for both Jews and Arabs or two states, one for each people. The &quot;bi-national&quot; state has never been realistic because the two sides don&#39;t trust each other to rule.&#0160; However, politicians on both sides resisted the more practical and just two state solution, refusing to recognize the other side&#39;s legitimate claims and rights.&#0160; But, intellectuals and practical people whose eyes were open to the injustice and instability of the situation began to realize that a two state solution was the only workable approach.&#0160; </p>
<p>In 1993, Jews and Arabs secretly negotiated the outline of a 2 state solution in Oslo, Norway, which has been called the Oslo Accord.&#0160; In 2000, the prime minister of Israel and the leader of the PLO came close, but ultimately failed to establish a 2-state solution in negotiations held at Camp David in the United States.&#0160; A Palestinian intellectual (Sari Nusseibeh) and the former leader of the Shin Bet Israeli equivalent of the FBI (Ami Ayalon ) published a &quot;Destination Roadmap&quot; which went even further and addressed the final questions that must be answered in a complete peace settlement. The answers are known and have been proposed jointly by both sides more than once.&#0160; But, both sides are politically unstable and can&#39;t get their own people to agree and accept these plans. </p>
<p>There have been three Palestinian uprisings, each called &quot;Intifada&quot; (or &quot;shaking off&quot; in Arabic), against Israel:&#0160; in 1987, in 2000 (after deliberate provocation by Israeli ex-general Ariel Sharon), and in 2008.&#0160; In 2000, Israel granted very limited autonomy to the PLO and Palestinian Authority to administer the West Bank under Israeli military authority.&#0160; In 2005, after it became clear that it was impossible to hold the Gaza Strip or get Israelis to settle there, Ariel Sharon, the most ruthless of Israeli former generals who was then prime minister of Israel, withdrew all Israeli settlers and Israeli military from the Gaza Strip&#8211;leaving it to the Palestinian Authority.&#0160; In 2006 under US pressure, the Palestinan Authority held elections in Gaza and a group called Hamas won.&#0160; Hamas is publicly committed to the destruction of Israel.&#0160; In 2009, right wing parties, committed to increasing settlements and controlling the Palestinian&#39;s territory were elected in Israel because of the increasing violence in Gaza.&#0160; Both sides have hardened their positions against a 2-state solution, even though 65% of Israeli citizens support a 2-state solution.</p>
<p>This may seem like a long blog post, but it is about the shortest way to give a very bare outline of what happened, leaving out many of the nuances and underlying causes of the situation.&#0160;&#0160; Israel believes the world is against it and Arabs, who outnumber Israelis 130 to 1, are poised to destroy Israel.&#0160; The founding myth of Israel lives on: that Israel must defend itself in a hostile world.&#0160; Palestinians believe that Israel will never yield and will continue to control their territory and suppress their rights so that only eliminating Israel will restore their land, rights, and self-respect.&#0160; Many opportunities for peace have been missed.&#0160; Leadership on both sides is fractured by conflict and instability&#8211;neither side can make a hard decision that involves compromise.&#0160; Neither side will accept a bi-national state for fear the other side will control it.&#0160; Neither side will accept a two-state solution until it gets a better deal.&#0160; And that, then, is the situation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../2009/02/the-situation/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">26</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lunch</title>
		<link>./../2009/02/lunch/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../2009/02/lunch/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2009 12:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Chron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://192.168.1.90/israel/?p=25</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Lunch at a hummous joint in the Arab quarter souk in Jerusalem was great: &#8211; ground lamb in some kind of yellow-ish broth &#8211; awesome pita bread—way better than the bread-disks we get in the US &#8211; their jalapenos aren’t that hot &#8211; simply amazing pickles &#8211; lots of other things stewing on the stove [&#038;hellip]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lunch at a hummous joint in the Arab quarter souk in Jerusalem was great:</p>
<p>&#8211; ground lamb in some kind of yellow-ish broth</p>
<p>&#8211; awesome pita bread—way better than the bread-disks we get in the US</p>
<p>&#8211; their jalapenos aren’t that hot</p>
<p>&#8211; simply amazing pickles</p>
<p>&#8211; lots of other things stewing on the stove</p>
<p>Here is the establishment and proud owner:</p>
<p><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/lunch.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-98" title="lunch" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/lunch-225x300.png" alt="" width="225" height="300" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/lunch-225x300.png 225w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/lunch.png 360w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../2009/02/lunch/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">25</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Day in Old Jerusalem</title>
		<link>./../2009/02/day-in-old-jerusalem/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../2009/02/day-in-old-jerusalem/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2009 12:34:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Chron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://192.168.1.90/israel/?p=24</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Just a few highlights here… clockwise, from upper left: &#8211; the Dome of the Rock Mosque &#8211; praying and photographing at the Western Wall of the Temple Mount &#8211; young Hasidic man]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Just a few highlights here…</p>
<table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="10" width="600">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="300" valign="top"><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/dome-of-the-rock.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-72" title="dome of the rock" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/dome-of-the-rock-300x200.png" alt="" width="250" height="166" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/dome-of-the-rock-300x200.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/dome-of-the-rock.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /></a></td>
<td width="300" valign="top"><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/praying.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-120" title="praying" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/praying-300x200.png" alt="" width="250" height="166" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/praying-300x200.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/praying.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="300" valign="top"><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/hasid.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-83" title="hasid" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/hasid-300x200.png" alt="" width="250" height="166" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/hasid-300x200.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/hasid.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 250px) 100vw, 250px" /></a></td>
<td width="300" valign="top">clockwise, from upper left:</p>
<h5>&#8211; the Dome of the Rock Mosque</h5>
<h5>&#8211; praying and photographing at the Western Wall of the Temple Mount</h5>
<h5>&#8211; young Hasidic man</h5>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../2009/02/day-in-old-jerusalem/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">24</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Big Tourist Day</title>
		<link>./../2009/02/big-tourist-day/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../2009/02/big-tourist-day/index.html#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2009 10:57:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Chron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://192.168.1.90/israel/?p=23</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Did the tourist big 3 today:  Masada, Qumran, and the Dead Sea. Masada was where 900 or more Jews held out against the Romans in 73AD.  On the last night when holding any longer appeared impossible, the Jewish Zealots drew lots for who would kill whom in order, and the last man committed suicide.  It [&#038;hellip]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Did the tourist big 3 today:  Masada, Qumran, and the Dead Sea.</p>
<p>Masada was where 900 or more Jews held out against the Romans in 73AD.  On the last night when holding any longer appeared impossible, the Jewish Zealots drew lots for who would kill whom in order, and the last man committed suicide.  It is a stirring site and the star of Israeli archaeology.   My anthropologist guide points out that the story is very unlikely to be true:  skeletal remains of only about 30 people have ever been found despite years of digging.  It’s still an impressive site that shows how advanced the Jewish culture of 2000 years ago was.</p>
<p>It’s bizarre to hike <em>up</em> 400 meters (over 1300 feet) and only get back to sea level.  Lots of school groups with armed guards.   Lots of Uzi’s carried non-chalantly by twenty year olds.</p>
<p>Qumran is where the Dead Sea Scrolls were found.  My anthropogist guide specializes in analyzing human remains and ancient feces.  He has a convincing account that supports the view that a cult called the Essenes certainly lived at the Qumran site until 60-70AD. It was fun to hear how much the study of poo can teach us about how early people lived (Essenes weren’t very sanitary).  It seems that present-day Christians are much more interested in this site than religious Jews.  The modern day Christian pilgrims are looking for evidence that links the Old Testament to the New Testament, though there isn’t any in the Dead Sea scrolls.  The religious Jews really don’t want to find out that there were more than one version of the Old Testament—it would be confusing.</p>
<p>OK, the Dead Sea “beach” is a pit attracting some of the most unlovely specimens of humanity to don bathing suits.  You really can float.  Not only can you float on your back, but you can float feet down/straight up with your chest, shoulders and head above the water.  This is acrid water—you can sort of tolerate getting a taste of sea water when you lick your lips when you swim in the ocean.  But, the Dead Sea tastes like you are in some kind of chemical bath.  I can’t tell if my skin is more vibrant now, but it was very refreshing after the hot hike up Masada.  The other cool thing is even with the sun beating down you can’t get sunburnt.  The atmosphere is so thick at this low elevation below sea level that most UV rays are cut.</p>
<p>Continue to see some pictures&#8230;</p>
<p><span id="more-23"></span></p>
<table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="10" width="600">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="300" valign="top"><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/masada-summit.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-103" title="masada summit" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/masada-summit-300x225.png" alt="" width="300" height="225" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/masada-summit-300x225.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/masada-summit.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></td>
<td width="300" valign="top">The summit of Masada:  about 1M above sea level, but 400M above the Dead Sea.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="300" valign="top"><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/masada-walls.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-104" title="masada walls" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/masada-walls-300x200.png" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/masada-walls-300x200.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/masada-walls.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></td>
<td width="300" valign="top">Restored walls on the summit of Masada, part of King Herod’s castle and defensive fortification built circa 30 BCE.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="300" valign="top"><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/joe-masada.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-93" title="joe masada" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/joe-masada-200x300.png" alt="" width="200" height="300" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/joe-masada-200x300.png 200w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/joe-masada.png 320w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></a></td>
<td width="300" valign="top">Joe Zias, curmudgeonly guide, who delights in bursting archaeologically based bubbles, especially bubbles dear to dogmatic religious types.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="300" valign="top"><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/beach.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-64" title="beach" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/beach-300x200.png" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/beach-300x200.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/beach.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></td>
<td width="300" valign="top">The beach at the Dead Sea, very popular with largish Russians and Germans.  Hills of Jordan in the background beyond the Dead Sea.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="300" valign="top"><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/swimmers.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-128" title="swimmers" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/swimmers-300x200.png" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/swimmers-300x200.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/swimmers.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></td>
<td width="300" valign="top">Swimmers or should I say “floaters.”  In addition to amazing floating, it appears to be popular to smear yourself with thick green mud from the bottom.  I didn’t try that; I don’t like “treatments.”</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="300" valign="top"><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/east-jeru.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-73" title="east jeru" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/east-jeru-300x200.png" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/east-jeru-300x200.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/east-jeru.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></td>
<td width="300" valign="top">View of East Jerusalem (Palestinian) from the Mount of Olives.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="300" valign="top"><a href="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/jeru-vista.png"><img loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-90" title="jeru vista" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/jeru-vista-300x200.png" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/jeru-vista-300x200.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2010/01/jeru-vista.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></td>
<td width="300" valign="top">Sunset over Jerusalem with Dome of the Rock and Al Aqsa Mosque visible.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../2009/02/big-tourist-day/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">23</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Behind on Blogs</title>
		<link>./../2009/03/behind-on-blogs/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../2009/03/behind-on-blogs/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2009 01:52:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Chron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://192.168.1.90/israel/?p=22</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To all (?) my loyal readers, I am sorry I’ve gotten behind on new items that I know (?) you are anxiously awaiting.&#0160; I got a terrible cold as the result of not sleeping because of jet lag, while still charging around unabated during the days.&#0160; For two nights I was too tired to blog. [&#038;hellip]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To all (?) my loyal readers,</p>
<p>I am sorry I’ve gotten behind on new items that I know (?) you are anxiously awaiting.&#0160; I got a terrible cold as the result of not sleeping because of jet lag, while still charging around unabated during the days.&#0160; For two nights I was too tired to blog.</p>
<p>I’m back…</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../2009/03/behind-on-blogs/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">22</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tags</title>
		<link>./../2009/03/tags/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../2009/03/tags/index.html#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2009 01:59:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Chron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://192.168.1.90/israel/?p=21</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am starting a new “tag” for impressions so that I can say how what I am seeing and hearing affects me and what I think about it. The tags in this blog are: &#8211; Chron&#0160; &#8212; updates on travels and activities, more or less in order &#8211; Map –- yes, maps &#8211; Itinerary&#0160;– what [&#038;hellip]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am starting a new “tag” for impressions so that I can say how what I am seeing and hearing affects me and what I think about it.</p>
<p><strong></strong></p>
<p>The tags in this blog are:</p>
<p>&#8211; <strong>Chron&#0160; &#8212; </strong>updates on travels and activities, more or less in order</p>
<p>&#8211; <strong>Map –-</strong> yes, maps</p>
<p><strong>&#8211;</strong> <strong>Itinerary</strong>&#0160;<strong>–</strong> what we are doing, when and where</p>
<p><strong>&#8211;</strong> <strong>Books</strong>&#0160;<strong>–</strong> recommended reading to understand the situation here</p>
<p><strong>&#8211;</strong> <strong>Background</strong>&#0160;<strong>–</strong> historical information and perspective to help understand how the past continues to affect the present here</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../2009/03/tags/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">21</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
