<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Itinerary &#8211; Israel Study Tour</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2009 01:18:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7</generator>
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">180112064</site>	<item>
		<title>Israel Trip</title>
		<link>./../../../2009/02/israel-trip/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../2009/02/israel-trip/index.html#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2009 01:18:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Itinerary]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://192.168.1.90/israel/?p=31</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Later this week I am going to Israel for the first time.&#0160; Now is an exciting time, to say the least:&#0160; the violence in Gaza, Israeli elections, the economic downturn.&#0160; What?&#0160; Am I nuts?&#0160;&#0160; What better time to go! It’s my first time and I am doing a lot: Private touring: (February 21-25) Jerusalem:&#0160; the [&#038;hellip]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Later this week I am going to Israel for the first time.&#0160; Now is an exciting time, to say the least:&#0160; the violence in Gaza, Israeli elections, the economic downturn.&#0160; What?&#0160; Am I nuts?&#0160;&#0160; What better time to go!</p>
<p>It’s my first time and I am doing a lot:</p>
<ul>
<li>Private touring: (February 21-25)
<ul>
<li>Jerusalem:&#0160; the birthplace of Western Religion(s) (3)
<li>Masada:&#0160; the last stance and suicide of Jewish defenders against Rome
<li>Qumran:&#0160; site of the Dead Sea Scrolls excavation
<li>the Galilee:&#0160; hills and forests
<li>Haifa, Ceasarea, and Akko (Accre):&#0160; in order, Jews and Israeli Arabs co-existing peacefully and the largest Baha’i temple; Roman ruins; the most Arab of Israeli cities </li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</ul>
<li>Jordan tour (February 26-28):&#0160;
<ul>
<li>Amman, ancient Philadelphia and the capital of Jordan
<li>Madaba (settled for 4500 years) and most important Christian center in Jordan
<li>Mt. Nebo, where Moses first saw the Promised Land
<li>Kerak, a crusader castle—thankfully the only one I’ll bother with
<li>Petra, ancient capital of the Nabateans carved out of rock in the 4th century BCE—and one of the filming locations for Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade </li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</li>
</ul>
<p><span id="more-31"></span></p>
<ul>
<li>Study Tour with the New Israel Fund (<a href="http://www.nif.org/" target="_blank">link</a>) in Jerusalem, Galilee, Tel Aviv, Negev, Ashdod (March 1-10) :
<ul>
<li>“Current Challenges Facing Israeli Society,” Professor Naomi Chazan, NIF president and former speaker of the Knesset
<li>“Safeguarding Democracy and Human Rights in Israel,” Association of Civil Rights in Israel
<li>Visit to Supreme Court of Israel (which recently blocked an attempt to prevent Arab parties from participating in elections to the Knesset)
<li>Meeting with members of the Knesset (Israel’s parliament) from different parties
<li>Tour of Jerusalem’s Nachlaot area (neighborhood built just outside the old Jewish quarter)
<li>One City for Two People:&#0160; tour of the heinous separation barrier built by Ariel Sharon and Ehud Olmert
<li>tour of Ofrah, one of the earliest Jewish settlements in the Occupied Territories of the West Bank, including a meeting with a defender of the settlements
<li>tour of Gedera, a Jewish Ethiopian community
<li>“Status of Women in Israel Today,” Anat Hoffman, Director of the Israel Religious Action Center of the Reform Movement
<li>tour of Moshav Kerem Maharal—a moshav is a cooperative agricultural community centered on families, often with private ownership of farm plots
<li>relax at a spa in the Galilee
<li>“Promoting Democracy Education”
<li>tour of Safed, early Jewish settlement, home of Kabbalah—Jewish mysticism, conquered by the crusaders and then the Mamluks.&#0160; It is now Israel’s art capital.
<li>visit Emek HaEleh Winery, with samples?
<li>“Religious Pluralism,” Professor Moshe Halbertal
<li>Shabbat service
<li>tour old city of Jerusalem
<li>“Outlook for Peace – a Palestinian’s Perspective,” Professor <strong>Sari Nusseibeh</strong> of Al Quds University and author of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Once-Upon-Country-Palestinian-Life/dp/0374299501" target="_blank">Once Upon a Country</a>, an absolutely fabulous book by a delightfully thoughtful man—this will be <em>the</em> highlight for me.
<li>“An Israeli Journalist’s Perspective on the Current Mood in Israel,” Isabel Kershner of the New York Times
<li>“Current Issues in Human Trafficking and Refugees,” Shevy Korzen of the Hotline for Migrant Workers
<li>“Community and Business Partnerships for Social Change,” Shula Keshet
<li>view Bauhaus architecture in Tel Aviv
<li>dinner with Israel government spokesperson, Miri Eisen
<li>“Addressing the Needs of the Negev in Be’er Sheva,” Yarona Ben Shalom
<li>“Economic Empowerment for Bedouin Women at Sidreh,” a Bedouin village in the Negev Desert in Israel’s south
<li>tour Ashdod, Israel’s primary port on the Mediterranean Sea
<li>tour Diaspora Museum – the “Diaspora” refers to the spreading out of a people from its ancestral home. For Jews, the original Diaspora was the flight to Babylon.
<li>tour Natan Guttman museum </li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Phew!&#0160; What a trip!&#0160; I’m not tired; I’m energized.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../2009/02/israel-trip/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">31</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
